Guide to the Joan E. Biren photograph collection, 1971-1991 MS2019
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Joan E. Biren photograph collection
1971-1991
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Biren, Joan E.
MS2019
1.5 Linear Feet
Collection consists of photographs both black and white and color used in the exhibit Queerly Visible, 1971-1991: The Work of JEB (Joan E. Biren), A Washington Photographer, which appeared at The Gelman Library's Special Collections Department from September 4, 1997-February 28, 1998. The captions that were used in the exhibit have been included with each photo. These images relate to the gay and lesbian community in Washington, D.C. and throughout the United States.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by Joan E. Biren
Biographical Note
Joan Elisabeth Biren, also known as JEB, was born in Washington, D.C. on July 13, 1944. She has gained recognition as an outstanding documentary artist, and for over twenty years has been photographing, publishing and producing videos that chronicle the lives and times of lesbian and gay people.
As a video producer for the 1993 March on Washington for Lesbian, Gay and Bi Equal Rights and Liberation, JEB was responsible for sending a live six-camera switched feed to giant screens on the Mall and around the world via satellite. Many commentators noted that this innovative use of the technology was brilliantly accomplished. JEB produced and wrote "A Simple Matter of Justice," the official video of the March. This one-hour piece was voted "Best Video" at the Reel Affirmations Film Festival in Washington, D.C.
With Moonforce Media, the company of which she is president, JEB produces, directs and edits videos. Recent projects include tapes on sexual harassment and city youth in performance. Moonforce Media and JEB have released "Lesbian Physicians on Practice, Patients and Power," which is widely used in medical schools, and For Love and for Life: The 1987 march on Washington for Lesbian and Gay Rights, which was broadcast on public television.
JEB is the author of two groundbreaking volumes of photography. "Eye to Eye: Portraits of Lesbians (1979)" is the pioneering photographic book that made lesbian existence and courage visible as never before. "Making a Way: Lesbians Out Front (1987)" is a beautiful, vigorous affirmation of lesbian lives that dramatically portrays 125 women. JEB's photographic work is in the collection of the Library of Congress, has been exhibited at the Lincoln Center in New York and published extensively in books, periodicals and newspapers, on music album covers, as well as on note cards, post cards and posters. Her multi-image slide presentations, which have toured throughout the United States, include the historical and autobiographical work OUT OF BOUNDS: A LESBIAN JOURNEY.
Biren has a B.A. with honors in political science from Mt. Holyoke College and an M.A. in communications from the American University. After three years in a doctoral program at Oxford University in England, she returned to the U.S. and taught herself photography working in a camera store and on a small-town newspaper. Since 1975, JEB has supported herself as a freelance photographer and independent videomaker.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection consists of photographs both black and white and color used in the exhibit Queerly Visible, 1971-1991: The Work of JEB (Joan E. Biren), A Washington Photographer, which appeared at The Gelman Library's Special Collections Department from September 4, 1997-February 28, 1998. The captions that were used in the exhibit have been included with each photo. These images relate to the gay and lesbian community in Washington, D.C. and throughout the United States.
Collection Organization
Organized in two series: Prints (11x14) and Prints (16x20).
Gay men; Washington (D.C.); Protest movements; AIDS (Disease); Gays; Lesbians; Photographs; Warhol, Andy; Mosbacher, Dee; Gartrell, Nanette; Lorde, Audre; Lyon, Phyllis; Martin, Del; Biren, Joan E.; Brown, Rita Mae
- Prints (11x14), 1971-1991; MS2019 Series 1; 1 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of fifty-five prints. The material covers from 1971-91. These images represent many gay and lesbian events and gatherings in Washington, D.C and other cities. These events include booksignings at Lambda Rising Bookstore, the Michigan Womyn's Music Festival, and DC's annual Take Back the Night March. These images also include representation of people of signifiance in the gay and lesbian community including Dr. Dee Mosbacher, Dr. Nanette Gartrell, Del Martin, Phyllis Lyon, Rita Mae Brown, Andy Warhol, and Audre Lorde.
  - Charlotte Bunch, with other members of The Furies, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-1-PRI
  - Mary-Helen Mautner, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-2-PRI
  - The official portrait of the Lammas softball team, 1974 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-3-PRI
  - Rita Mae Brown at Lammas Bookstore's publication party for her novel Rubyfruit Jungle, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-4-PRI
  - Meg Christian's Farewell Concert in Washington, DC., 1975 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-5-PRI
  - Mary, Sue and Markie watch the ball game, 1976 June (Box 1, Folder 6)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-6-PRI
  - Partying to mark the 3rd anniversary of Lammas Women's Shop on Capitol Hill, 1976 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-7-PRI
  - Women of the DC Area Feminist Alliance meet at the Sumner School, 1977 September (Box 1, Folder 8)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-8-PRI
  - Mayo Lee, President, Gay Activists Alliance, pro-testing DC visit of Anita Bryant, 1978 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-9-PRI
  - Celebrating DC's 3rd annual Gay and Lesbian Pride Day, 1978 June (Box 1, Folder 10)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-10-PRI
  - Marion Barry campaigning for mayor at one of DC's gay bars, 1978 September (Box 1, Folder 11)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-11-PRI
  - Lori and Valerie working at Wrenchwoman, DC's all-woman automobile repair shop, 1978 October (Box 1, Folder 12)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-12-PRI
  - Mabel Hampton, 1978 November (Box 1, Folder 13)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-13-PRI
  - Randy and Tara, 1979 May (Box 1, Folder 14)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-14-PRI
  - Darquita and Denyeta, 1979 June (Box 1, Folder 15)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-15-PRI
  - Rusty Slesinger playing pool at "The Phase"at 8th Street, S.E., 1979 June (Box 1, Folder 16)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-16-PRI
  - Dot Palmerton, D.C. Chef, 1979 July (Box 1, Folder 17)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-17-PRI
  - Gay and Lesbian Pride Day, Los Angeles, 1980 June (Box 1, Folder 18)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-18-PRI
  - Sarah Shulman and members of the Women's Libera-tion Zap Action Brigade are arrested for disrupting the US Senate hearings on an anti-abortion bill, 1981 April (Box 1, Folder 19)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-19-PRI
  - DC's annual Take Back the Night March, to protest violence against women, goes through the heart of the red light district, 1981 September (Box 1, Folder 20)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-20-PRI
  - Tacie Dejanikus in the office of the radical feminist newspaper off our backs, 1981 October (Box 1, Folder 21)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-21-PRI
  - At the second Women's Pentagon Action, women engaging in non-violent civil disobedience block the entrances, 1981 November (Box 1, Folder 22)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-22-PRI
  - Barbara Deming (1917-1984), 1981 December (Box 1, Folder 23)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-23-PRI
  - Elana Dykewomon, 1982 October (Box 1, Folder 24)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-24-PRI
  - Lammas softball team at bat on a field near the Lincoln Memorial, 1983 July (Box 1, Folder 25)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-25-PRI
  - Mauve and Brenda building a boardwalk for the differently-abled at the 8th Michigan Womyn's Music Festival, 1983 August (Box 1, Folder 26)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-26-PRI
  - Aime and J. at the workers' kitchen at the 8th Michigan Womyn's Music Festival, 1983 August (Box 1, Folder 27)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-27-PRI
  - Dr. Dee Mosbacher and Dr. Nanette Gartrell vacationing in Colorado, 1984 June (Box 1, Folder 28)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-28-PRI
  - Del Martin and Phyllis Lyon, 1984 July (Box 1, Folder 29)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-29-PRI
  - J. Casselberry and Jacque DuPree at the 9th Michigan Womyn's Music Festival, 1984 August (Box 1, Folder 30)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-30-PRI
  - Boys' camp at the 9th Michigan Womyn's Music Festival, 1984 August (Box 1, Folder 31)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-31-PRI
  - Parading down Connecticut Avenue on DC's Gay and Lesbian Pride Day, 1985 June (Box 1, Folder 32)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-32-PRI
  - Andy Warhol signs his book America at Lambda Rising Bookstore on Connecticut Avenue, 1985 October (Box 1, Folder 33)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-33 PRI
  - Claire Olivia Moed and Joan Nestle at the 10th anniversary celebration of the Lesbian Herstory Archives (LHA) in New York City, 1986 April (Box 1, Folder 34)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-34-PRI
  - A DC lesbian mother's group stroller brigade at the pro-choice March for Women's Lives, 1986 March 09 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-35-PRI
  - Michelle Parkerson and Storme DeLarvie filming Storme: the Lady of the Jewel Box, 1986 October (Box 1, Folder 36)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-36-PRI
  - Gay and Lesbian elected officials, serving in state, county and municipal governments, gather at the Capitol, 1986 November (Box 1, Folder 37)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-37-PRI
  - Rabbi Linda Holtzman reads the Torah at Beth Ahavah, Philadelphia's gay and lesbian synagogue, 1987 February (Box 1, Folder 38)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-38-PRI
  - Audre Lorde (1934-1992), 1987 May (Box 1, Folder 39)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-39-PRI
  - Kim and Robin conversing in American Sign Language, 1987 June (Box 1, Folder 40)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-40-PRI
  - Leonard Matlovich is arrested in front of the White House Protesting the Reagan Administration's lack of action on AIDS, 1987 June (Box 1, Folder 41)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-41-PRI
  - Urvashi Vaid, Executive Director, and Sue Hyde, Field Organizer, of the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force at DC's Gay and Lesbian Pride Parade, 1987 June (Box 1, Folder 42)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-42-PRI
  - Inaugural display of the NAMES Project AIDS Memorial Quilt, second national March on Washington for Lesbian and Gay Rights, 1987 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-43-PRI
  - People with AIDS contingent marching on Pennsylvania Avenue in the second national March on Washington for Lesbian and Gay Rights, 1987 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-44-PRI
  - Rally crowd on the Mall at the second national March on Washington for Lesbian and Gay Rights, 1987 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-45-PRI
  - Bowers vs. Hardwick decision protest, 1987 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-46-PRI
  - Perry Watkins and another mourner at Leonard Matlovit's funeral in Congressional Cemetery, 1988 July (Box 1, Folder 47)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-47-PRI
  - Candlelight vigil at the Lincoln Memorial for people with AIDS as part of ceremonies organized by the NAMES Project, 1988 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-48-PRI
  - Protest at the Food and Drug Administration Head-quarters, by national alliance of ACT UP (AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power) chapters, 1988 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-49-PRI
  - Mary-Helen Mautner with her daughter and friends at a Jewish Lesbian Chanukah party, 1988 December (Box 1, Folder 50)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-50-PRI
  - Cheering on the marchers at the 20th anniversary of the Stonewall Rebellion, 1989 June (Box 1, Folder 51)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-51-PRI
  - Members of OUT and others protest the cancellation of the Mapplethorpe exhibit at the Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1989 June (Box 1, Folder 52)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-52-PRI
  - Spectators at the New York parade commemorating the 20th anniversary of the Stonewall Rebellion, 1989 June (Box 1, Folder 53)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-53-PRI
  - The AIDS Memorial Quilt displayed in its entirety on the Ellipse by the NAMES Project, 1989 October (Box 1, Folder 54)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-54-PRI
  - Phranc, punk rocking folksinger, and Holly Hughes, playwright and performance artist, take time out at the NGLTF Creating Change Conference, 1991 November (Box 1, Folder 55)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-55-PRI
- Prints (16x20), 1975-1987; MS2019 Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series consists of five prints. These images date from 1975-87. The subjects relate to the gay and lesbian community in Washington, D.C.
  - JEB in Dyke, Virginia, 1975 October (Box 1, Folder 56)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-2-1-PRI
  - Steve and Don, 1983 July (Box 1, Folder 57)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-2-2-PRI
  - The Queer & Present Danger affinity group at the U.S. Supreme Court, 1987 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-2-3-PRI
  - Priscilla and Regina sleeeping, 1979 June (Box 1, Folder 59)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-2-4-PRI
  - Mel Boozer (in suit and tie) with the Gay Activists Alliance contingent, 1987 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    [From original finding aid]: JEB-2-5-PRI